I think it's amazing to know when you
first find out that a sharp ratio a
point estimate of a Sharp ratio actually
doesn't mean much for example if we take
two Gans and we put them together in
different combinations with different
probabilities and sampling from
different normal distributions we can
end up with an array of different SKS
and kosis but with the exact same sharp
ratio so if that's the case then what's
the difference between sharp ratio well
essentially it's our confidence level
between our sharp ratios when we change
these high order moments so the skewness
and the kosis of our portfolio returns
then this really impacts our portfolio
standard deviation and our estimate
around our sharp ratio this is of utmost
importance because it greatly impacts
the confidence bands and consequently
its statistical significance so we're
going to be going through a paper from
Bailey and Lopez dto and we're going to
be going through start to finish and
what is the probabilistic sharp ratio
and how it can help you with your
analysis we'll be running through this
jupyter notebook and here I've just got
a diagram of what is the probabilistic
sharp ratio essentially what we're
trying to do we're trying to come up
with a probabilistic measure of how
confident we are that our sharp ratio
estimate is correct to what likelihood
can we say that our estimate is greater
than a particular Benchmark sharp ratio
now the sharp r ratio has long been the
go-to metric for evaluating investment
performance relative to risk however
it's got its own certain limitations so
first off if you have a strategy that
actually has excess returns and the
returns are independent and identically
distributed where you've got n um sets
of data that represent your returns then
you're modeling your returns normally so
around a me with a variance so this was
first introduced by sharp that we have a
point estimate of the sharp ratio so
this Sr hat where it's equal to the um
average mean returns minus some kind of
risk-free rate divided by our uh
standard deviation our estimate a
standard deviation of the returns so
what are the limitations well it's a
point estimate so it tells us nothing
about the uncertainty around this
estimate it assumes a normal
distribution which you can look in
literature is um highly debated of the
natural um distribution statistical
traits of return series um it's
inadequate for non
strategies penalizes upside volatility
and it's sensitive to time frames what
do I mean by sensitive to time frames I
mean that um due to aggregation of
returns like is done for hedge funds and
superannuation funds and um other
portfolio management funds where they're
only publishing returns data for example
over a quarterly basis like the 13fs
here this aggregation actually um
reduces the number of data points that
we have to judge returns and therefore
it affects our statistical significance
so let's understand the background of
where the probabilistic sharp ratio came
from so first off low published in the
statistics of sharp ratios paper that
assuming IID normal return so
independent and identically distributed
returns with a skew of zero and ketosis
of three an estimated sharp ratio would
follow a normal distribution with
standard deviation now Merton's Christie
and OB Dei published papers and they
actually described that the sharp ratio
estimate relaxing these assumptions of
normality and even Independence so
having stuff like serial correlation
between returns and relaxing the
Assumption and allowing for skew and
kosis in returns that again our estimate
of our sharp ratio is actually centered
around a normal distribution so this was
a critical finding in the development of
the probabilistic sharp ratio because
now we can actually relax those
normality assumptions okay so now I have
a sharp estimate that is centered around
a normal distribution even if it has
skew even if it has kosis and even if it
has some kind of Serial correlation so
that's great but why does it matter well
let's take a look at some a real world
example in the paper Bailey and Lopez D
essentially they came up with um a proof
that any combination of Gans as a
mixture model can create a certain sharp
ratio so let's take the mixture of two
gan to create a distribution with both
skew and kosis now the way we can do
that is we have two normally distributed
um normal distributions and then we're
going to be sampling from different
probabilities from different uh from the
two distributions now essentially what
they ask themselves is what is the
probability so that the mixture of the
two normal distributions such that I get
a certain sharp ratio so they allowed
the sharp ratio um that you're looking
for this the target sharp ratio equal to
the expectation of returns um normalized
by the variance or the standard
deviation so to understand this let's go
through the example in Python so import
your dependencies we've got npy Panda
Seaborn scipi and matplot lib um they
have certain conditions around this
probability so we need to actually
confirm some checks and verifications
for solving the probability to make sure
that it is possible and it is a unique
solution so in their paper you have
probability around this quadratic so you
end up with two solutions so the first
thing we need to check um for the
solution that is a unique solution where
b^2 is greater than or equal to 4 a c
and we also need to make sure that we
generating the standard mean um uh mean
and standard pairs that are within
boundary conditions to make sure that
the probability sits between Zer and one
and those are defined by these
conditions so I've just coded these up
into these formulas here and all
formulas are within my medium post
that's in the description
below so I've got a check p is a unique
solution I've got check the sign because
we've got a quadratic formula and we
need to make sure that we're selecting
the right solution and we've got to
confirm p boundaries so now I'm going to
generate my mean standard pairs so I'm
going to create standard pairs of our
means and our standard deviations
randomly with a normal distribution for
means and then the half normal
distribution because you also always
need a positive variance so we're going
to confirm that these sit within the
boundary conditions if not we're going
to generate more so I'm going to
generate uh 1 million pairs of means and
standard deviations here and then I'm
going to create a function where I
calculate the p uh the probability of
Distributing to get a certain sharp
ratio now here I'm sending in the sharp
ratio through a Vector through an array
so here I'm calling the I've got a numpy
array and the First Column is the sharp
ratio Target so we calculate the
probabilities by applying this function
that we've just used across the axis and
across our data um along the aess and we
get our probabilities now the first
thing I want you to notice is that we
getting n uh We've getting Nas uh back
from our numpy solution and the reason
is because we're finding that when we
check for Unique Solutions sometimes
it's the case that um we're not getting
unique Solutions so b^2 is less than or
equal to 4 * a * C so what we need to do
is we're just going to filter for is na
um within our data set and then we get a
um we only get unique solutions back so
we have our means standard deviations
and probabilities that create a sharp
ratio of one so now we're going to use
those sets of Gan mixture models to
actually simulate and C calculate the
standard error around a sharp ratio so
I've got a function here which generates
my gum mixture model data given our
means and standard deviations and our
weights which is just that probability
metric and then I have a function that
calculates the standard error the
standard deviation of our sharp um ratio
estimate so here I'm just using a Monte
Carlo simulation where I have um a
number of data points per sample so I'm
just simulating one ,000 for all our
different um types of means and standard
deviations that fit within that Gan um
mixture model to create a sharp ratio of
one and if I plot that I just want to
show you that here we end up with all
these portfolios of a Sharp ratio of one
but where we have widely different
curtosis and skew so the main takeaway
here is that you can have very large um
tail risk and skewness in your returns
distributions that all all have a
theoretical uh true value of a Sharp
ratio of one so I what I'm about to show
you is that these higher moments really
matter for the confidence intervals and
especially when you have low data um for
example only 2 years worth of data or
less um with your hedge fund or with
your super annuation fund when you're
estimating returns this can lead to
inflated sharp
ratios so here I'm just going to plot
the same thing in plotly but you'll
notice that I did have the standard
deviation estimate of the sharp ratio so
I'm just plotting that although the
skewness in kosis does not affect the
point estimate of the sharp ratio
because obviously um that's as part of
the central limit theorem um but it does
impact heavily the confidence intervals
because the standard deviation of the
sharp ratio estimate changes with these
uh with these non-normal um statistical
attributes of skus and kosis so here you
can see a wide range of increasing
standard deviation of our sharp ratio as
you increase uh skewness decrease
skewness or increase kosis let's talk
about those sharp ratio confidence
intervals so in their paper they looked
at uh the standard deviation estimate
which is once you rearrange um the
formula before that we saw about the
distribution of our estimate of standard
deviation from literature you end up and
arrive at this formula so the nus1 comes
from the bessels correction and here
gamma 3 and Gamma 4 incorporate those so
gamma 3 is the skus and Gamma 4 is the
curtosis so now we're actually including
these higher order moments into our
standard um deviation estimate of our
sharp ratio so what does that look like
in Python well let's say that I have an
estimated sharp ratio of one and I have
a number of observations which is
realistic like eight so let's say
quarterly quarterly returns profile for
only 2 years history so I've got eight
returns calculate the standard deviation
and sharp ratio so we've got a formula
where we're taking in the sharp ratio
The Benchmark the number of observations
skus kosis and we're returning the
standard deviation as per this formula
so I calculate this um Sigma hat this
standard deviation for normal returns
and for a portfolio with non-normality
with skewness so negative skew and kosis
of 10 so now we're going to calculate
our two-sided confidence intervals so
we're going to take in a sharp ratio our
standard deviation and our confidence
level confidence um level is just going
to be a percentage as a fraction so 90%
is 0.9 we're going to return the lower
bound and upper bound of our two-sided
confidence interval so now we're going
to look at and print out just the
difference between a normal distributed
um distribution with the same sharp Rao
one and we can see that we have much
tighter bounds than a very large um
uncertainty around our non-normally
distributed with negative skew and high
curtosis so with only eight data points
we can see a vast difference in our
confidence levels um because of uh the
skus and the kosis so the higher and
lower confidence intervals of the
non-normal distributed highlight how
skus and kosis with limited number of
observations could cause significant
inflation of the simple Point estimate
of the sharp ratio so this is the main
point that I'm trying to bring home here
I'm just going to plot the confidence
intervals as data increases so as data
increases we get more confident about
our solution but I want to show you the
big difference between the normal
returns and the non-normal returns so
again here um the boundaries here as we
increase the number of observations
start to get Tighter and Tighter around
our true sharp ratio of one but for the
normal returns distribution you can see
that the confidence intervals are much
tighter to begin with at a lower number
of observations but when you have that
negative um when you have skus and when
you have curtosis it's we are much less
certain um much less confident at that
same percentage confidence level um with
that same number of data observations so
therefore for the risk adverse investor
it is absolutely critical to be aware um
of the skew and kosis present in your
returns distribution and be estimating
that and actually including clud that
within your sharp ratio estimate or at
least be aware of your um confidence
levels the main conclusion we want to
draw here is that the sharp ratio
estimates are very highly impacted by
two statistical traits one is the
non-normality so the skewness and the
kosis and one is the reduced granularity
so that returns aggregation that we
spoke about before when um hedge funds
are trying to reduce the uh the period
that they're actually publishing their
returns and therefore we have a lower
number of observ ations to calculate the
sharp Ratio or estimate the sharp ratio
so let's talk about the probability
sharp ratio now this was developed in
Bailey and Lopez D PR's paper and
essentially they're trying to come up
with a metric that incorporates this
uncertainty so they ask the question
what is the percentage likelihood that
our actual estimate sharp ratio is
greater than a benchmark sharp ratio so
the probability that our Benchmark sharp
ratio is um less than or equal to our
estim sharp ratio and here we're just
taking the integral of um the interval
from our estimated sharp ratio um down
to negative Infinity across the PDF of
the sharp ratio given our Benchmark
sharp ratio and our estimated standard
deviation so all we need to do is
integrate over the PDF and we get a that
our estimate of the probability sharp
ratio for a certain Benchmark is equal
to the cumulative distri um distribution
function with our parameters in here so
we've got the difference between our
estimate sharp ratio and our Benchmark
and we've just divided it by the
standard um deviation estimate so our
Bessel function um Square < TK nus1 has
ended up coming to the top and then we
had our
numerator before of our standard error
distribution that we talked about before
so all I'm going to do here is I'm going
to calculate that um in Python I'm going
to write the function we're going to
bring in a sharp ratio Benchmark sharp
ratio number of observations skus and
kosis and we're going to report the
probability sharp ratio so just using
the um stats normal cumulative
distribution function of the um
difference between our sharp ratio
estimate and our Benchmark sharp ratio
divided by um the standard deviation the
volatility so just showing showing an
example there if we had a strategy sharp
ratio estimate of .5 a benchmark of3
skus of minus point2 and a kosis of 3.5
and a number of observations that's
extremely high so let's say this is just
one year but 252 trading days we're very
confident that our sharp ratio is
greater than our Benchmark sharp ratio
of 0.3 and would be
99.7% confident now let's talk about a
trickier situation than the one where we
have high amounts of data so here we had
252 observations more likely we have
something like eight so here we're going
to talk about two portfolios with the
same true sharp ratio the TR same true
sharp ratio is going to be 1.5 so a very
good sharp ratio we're going to have
returns that are normally distributed
for one of the portfolios and returns
that are non-normally distributed with a
skew of minus 1.2 and a ketosis of
approximately 3 5.3 so the way we're
going to Cal create this non-normally
distributed um IID process is we're
going to use the giian mixture model
again as we had before so here I just
need to calculate the probability um
again using the formulas before from the
paper from uh Bailey and Lopez dto to
get my true sharp ratio of 1.5 for this
non-normal distributed um portfolio so
essentially um once I calculate this and
I've just chosen a mean um for my normal
distribution as 4 so 40% annualized
returns and then therefore I can change
the scale to then get my desired um
sharp ratio for my normal so all I'm
doing is taking the mean and divide it
by 1.5 to get my standard deviation and
here I can just plot what those two
portfolio returns would look like so
essentially without my two Gan um
distributions I've got this green Gan
distribution down here at only an 8%
probability that I'm sampling from it so
this is very realistic scenario where
you've got some kind of portfolio
manager who has this really um you know
small chance of very low returns so
we've got large tail risk but it's at a
low probability that we're actually
going to be drawing from this so 8% of
the time versus this Gan one process
where we've got nice positive returns
and then the combination of this gussian
mixture model is in blue and you can see
that it's just following those two
distrib tions now with the exact same
sharp ratio true sharp ratio we've got
this normal distribution in Red so we
can see sitting a little bit lower um
than our blue distribution mode but has
the same sharp ratio and this and very
different characteristics so let's
identify how hard it is to actually get
a true estimate um or an accurate
estimate of our standard deviation when
we only have a limited number of data
points so let's say we want to compare
these two portfolios only over two years
of quarterly data to estimate the sharp
ratios remember that these are unseen
processes we don't know what the skus
and the kosis is of our Gan mixture
model portfolio 2 and we don't know what
they what our what the distribution is
for our normal distribution I just want
to calculate the sharp ratios I want to
calculate the probabilistic sharp ratio
the confidence intervals and then the
higher order moments around both
portfolios so skew and kosis we're going
to take only eight data points from each
sample them and we're going to try and
estimate the sharp
ratio so in a very similar fashion I'll
let you take a look at your code in the
spare time but essentially um what I
want to show you is that as we run this
again and again and
again we we find that the portfolio
estimate um sharp ratio is actually
pretty accurate with only eight data
points for the portfolio that has an
normal distribution so we're even
getting a sharp ratio close to 1.5 here
and we're saying that the probability of
the sharp ratio that it's greater than
zero is very high it's nearly 100% we're
seeing our confidence intervals are
quite tight around 1.5 for only day
eight uh data points and the moment skew
is close to zero and um the kosis is a
bit off there but again we've only got
eight data points now the difference is
look at the portfolio distribution for
the sharp ratio here here we have
1.88 but I want you to see if I run this
again for the non-normal distribution
just how different it is
1.99 let's run it
again here it's
3.96 I only ran it three times and in
that time just with our sampling of that
distribution we've now got a sharp ratio
that's significantly inflated and has a
sharp ratio estimate of nearly four so
this is an example of a a realistic
example where we've got this unseen
process with significant true downside
risk but because of the low frequency 8%
of drawing from this distribution most
of the time everything's okay and we're
Distributing from this this higher uh
distribution here gan1 where we're
actually then um getting a biased
estimate of the true distribution
so this is the difficulty and this
observation here naturally leads us to
think how long should a track record B
in order for us to have statistical
confidence that its sharp ratio is above
a given threshold so this is just asking
the probability of um of the sharp ratio
in a different way we're saying how long
do we actually need to observe um this
portfolio with different skews and
curtosis to be confident um that it's
above a given threshold and this is very
topical because when you have limited
data like eight data points here even
the normally distributed portfolio is
hard to get a true estimate on and
especially when uh we have we start
having portfolios with higher order
magnitude we do see that inflated sharp
ratio estimate um so this is the
question that we're going to address in
our next article so just summarizing
there um the main findings are that the
probabilistic sharp ratio is very
important to incorporate because we're
incorporating from the non-normal
characteristics that definitely impact
the statistical significance of our
sharp ratio estimate therefore by using
this probability probabilistic sharp
ratio we can reduce the rate of
discovery of false positive or type 1
errors the other finding from their
paper was high frequency reporting would
be preferred so portfolios with
undesirable statistical traits like with
ski and curosis the this p Pap advocates
for the highest reporting frequency that
doesn't violate the IID independently in
um and identically distributed
assumption enhancing the reliability of
these performance metrics because as
we've seen the higher the um frequency
of reporting the larger the number of
observations and therefore the more
confident we can be around our estimate
so in the next episode we're going to
look at what the minimum track record is
for different portfolios given certain
statistics IAL properties so until then
if you like the video give it a thumbs
up if you want to see the code um the
code is in my repository within my
Discord Channel or it's available free
on my medium post so until next time
YouTube see you
[Music]
later